Boy, the year's already over, huh?
(神楽)あ～ 今年も
もう終わりｱﾙな～｡
(銀時)早えな
もう やんなっちゃうな｡
Sure was fast.
I hate how the years go by faster as we get older.
歳とるごとに 早くなっていくよ
１年過ぎるのが｡
この調子じゃあ
じじいになったときは➡
At this rate, by the time I'm an old geezer,
Ｆ１ｶｰが 通り過ぎる並みのｽﾋﾟｰﾄﾞで
１年が 過ぎるんじゃねえの？
the years will pass at the speed of a Formula 1 car.
I've still got a long ways to go.
(神楽)私は まだまだ
大丈夫ｱﾙ｡
Well, I'm already up to Ben Johnson speed, I'd say.
いやいや 実際
ｵﾚなんかもう➡
ﾍﾞﾝ･ｼﾞｮﾝｿﾝが 走り去るくらいの
速さまで来てるからね もう｡
来てるからね そこにﾍﾞﾝが｡
My Ben Johnson is already up to here.
[Note: In Japanese, Ben also refers to Poop. So here Gin is referring to his incontinence.]
お前らも 若いからって
調子にのってると➡
Don't get too cocky because you're all still young.
すぐ来るよ｡ ﾍﾞﾝが｡
Your Ben Johnson will fall behind soon enough.
For real?
ﾏｼﾞかよ ﾍﾞﾝが来るのかよ｡
Ben Johnson's gonna fall out?
私 ﾍﾞﾝよりｶｰﾙのほうがいいね｡
かっけぇある｡
I prefer Carl Lewis over Ben Johnson.
He's cooler.
Well, all I'm saying is, we all had a pretty good year, right?
まぁ 要は
今年も充実した１年を➡
送ったってことじゃなくね？
(新八)送ってねえよ!!
まだ ２月だぞ!!
Hell no!
It's still February!
っていうか この会話
去年とまったく同じじゃねえか!!
And didn't we have the exact same conversation last year?!
だってこれ まるまる
使いまわしのﾊﾞﾝｸだもん｡
That's 'cause this whole segment was recycled.
そうだよ ｾﾘﾌどころか
画まで まったく同じｱﾙよ｡
Yeah.
Not just the lines, but also the video's the same too.
もっとひどい
手抜きだろうが!!
That's even more of a half-assed job!
ちゃんと ﾏｼﾞﾒに
ｱﾆﾒ作ってたんだよ？
They've been working hard on this anime.
けどさ 吉原編に入ってから
毎週毎週 ﾊﾞﾄﾙばっかりでさ➡
But you know...
Once we got into the Yoshiwara arc, it's been battle after battle every week.
そりゃ ちゃんとｱﾆﾒみたいで
かっこいいから➡
Not that I really mind since it's all cool like a real JUMP anime,
ｵﾚは いいんだけどさ
ｽﾀｯﾌがね➡
but the staff was like...
｢ちょっと このへんで
ひと息入れてくんないと➡
"If we don't throw in a little break, we're going to go over budget."
最後まで予算がもたない｣
ってね｡
I keep telling you...
だから ﾃﾚﾋﾞで
ｶﾈの話はやめろって…｡
Stop talking about money on TV.
だいたい …の 半分くらいしか
予算がないのに➡
I mean, it's ridiculous to ask for the same number of battles as "XXX" when we only have half the budget.
同じくらいのﾊﾞﾄﾙを
やれってのがﾑﾘなんだよ｡
もともと こうやって
ﾀﾞﾗﾀﾞﾗしゃべってるのが前提で➡
Our budget was set on the premise that there would be loads of talking.
決められた予算だからね｡
We're in our fourth year while running the original production costs,
結局 ４年目になっても
制作費 お値段据え置きの➡
現状価格で 画面ｻｲｽﾞ
４:３のまんまだってさ｡
and we're still using a 4:3 aspect ratio.
ｳﾁのﾌﾞﾗｳﾝ管ﾃﾚﾋﾞには
ちょうどいいね｡
That's perfect for our piece of crap TV.
We live in a time where there's Hi-Vision and Blu-ray.
[Note: Hi-Vision is the Japanese equivalent to Hi-Def.]
世の中 ﾊｲﾋﾞｼﾞｮﾝだ
ﾌﾞﾙｰﾚｲだって時代によ➡
今どき 16:９じゃねえｱﾆﾒって
どんだけだよ？
Who makes anime that isn't 16:9 these days?
っていうか 今
４年目って言わなかった？
Hold it, did you just say "our fourth year"?
この番組って
３月で 終了じゃなかったの？
Wasn't this show supposed to end in March?
Season 3 ends in March.
ｼｰｽﾞﾝ３がね｡
で そのまま４月から➡
And then Season 4 starts in April.
ｼｰｽﾞﾝ４が
始まることになったから｡
あ～あ 本当は
『水戸黄門』みたいに➡
Man, I was hoping for something like "Mito Komon" where every time a season ended,
[Note: These terms refers to classic Samurai TV shows that have a break between seasons.]
第何部が終わると
『大岡越前』とか➡
they threw in "Ohoka Echizen" or "Edo wo Kiru" until the next season started.
『江戸を斬る』をはさんで
それを交互に続けていけば➡
If we alternated like that, we could get up to thirty-nine seasons...
第39部くらいまで いけたのに｡
いけねえよ!!
Like hell, we could!
っていうか ﾎﾞｸ騙されてたの!?
最終章 突入が➡
And did you all trick me?!
You're telling me that whole "Final Chapter" crap was really Season 3?!
ｼｰｽﾞﾝ３のだなんて！
どんな 終わる終わる詐欺だよ!!
What kind of series finale scam is this?!
誰だって 騙されるわ！
Anyone would be fooled!!
『水戸黄門』化計画
失敗ｱﾙ｡
Our "Mito Komon style production" plan failed.
And here we carefully planned out this anime to be a long-running series...
こっちは 原作が
30年後も続いていることを➡
想定した
長期ｱﾆﾒ化計画だったのによ｡
under the assumption that the manga would run for over three decades!
だいたい お前らが➡
Besides, thanks to you guys falling for this kind of marketing covers,
こんな あざといｼﾞｬｹｯﾄに釣られて
ﾊﾞﾝﾊﾞﾝ買うから➡
and buying all our DVDs, our original plan got all screwed!!
こっちの計画が
全部 ｵｼﾞｬﾝだよ｡
ちょっと！
いったい 誰に文句言ってんの!!
Hey! Hey!! HEY!!! Who the hell are you complaining to?!
ＤＶＤとか
もう買うなよ お前ら｡
Stop buying DVDs, people.
というわけで
ｼｰｽﾞﾝごとに休みを入れて➡
And so, since our plan for a long-running series with a short break every season has failed,
長期ｼﾘｰｽﾞ化する作戦が
失敗した以上➡
the Gin Tama anime will take an alternate route in its fourth year!
ｱﾆﾒ 『銀魂』は ４年目に向けて
迂回ﾙｰﾄに入る！
(新八/神楽)迂回ﾙｰﾄ!?
Alternate route?
When an anime catches up to a manga that's still running,
連載中のﾏﾝｶﾞに
ｱﾆﾒが追いついてしまったとき➡
ﾏﾝｶﾞとのﾘｰﾁを保つため
別ﾙｰﾄを通って遠回りし➡
it must take a roundabout path to stay within reach of the manga before it can rejoin the manga.
再び 合流するという作戦だ｡
だが これには
さまざまなﾘｽｸが伴う｡
However, there are a number of risks.
The anime could buy enough time for the manga to move on, only to be canceled.
せっかく
迂回ﾙｰﾄを通ったのに➡
遠く離れたところで力尽きて
打ち切られたり➡
合流した矢先に
原作が終了してしまったり｡
Or the manga ends right when the anime's about to rejoin.
合流するのが早すぎて➡
Or the anime and manga rejoin too early, and the anime has to diverge again in no time.
すぐまた 別のﾙｰﾄに
行かなくてはならなくなったり｡
あるいは 迂回している間に➡
Or in the process of diverging,
the characters or setting in the anime become so different,
ﾏﾝｶﾞとｱﾆﾒの設定や ｷｬﾗが
離れていってしまい➡
永遠に 合流できなくなって
しまったりすることがある｡
that they can never rejoin again.
まぁ そのときは
開き直って➡
Well, that's when they shamelessly remake the anime from the beginning again.
原作の頭から
再ｱﾆﾒ化したり➡
ｷｬﾗｸﾀｰｼｽﾃﾑと称して
ｷｬﾗだけ使って➡
Or they use the same characters to make a totally different anime.
作り始めたりすれば
いいわけだ｡
でも 『銀魂』って➡
But Gin Tama doesn't have that big of a storyline.
そんな大きな ｽﾄｰﾘｰﾗｲﾝが
あるわけじゃないから➡
迂回ﾙｰﾄって
作りにくいんじゃないですか？
Wouldn't it be hard to make an alternative route?
そうね 『銀魂』はいったい
どんな迂回ﾙｰﾄを通るね？
Yeah, what kind of alternative route is Gin Tama going to use?
That would be...
それは…｡
That would be?
That would be...
We bought ourselves four minutes today.
今日は ４分 迂回したな｡
(新八/神楽)だ～っ！
♪♪～
(百華)管制室には 行かせぬ!!
We won't let you go to the control room!
♪♪～
(百華)ぐわっ！
ﾊｯ!!
(百華)ぐはっ！
はぁぁぁ～っ!!
♪♪～
ﾁｨ… 一本 足んなかったね!!
Damn! One hand short!
ぐはっ！
よくやったね 新八！
Good job, Shinpachi!
(晴太)急ごう！
きっと この先に…！
Hurry!
I'm sure it's right up ahead!
["The Color for Each Person's Bond Comes in Various Colors"]
Go!!
(月詠)いっけ～!!
うぉぉぉ～っ!!
♪♪～
(鳳仙)ぐぉぉぉ～っ!!
ぐあぁぁぁ～っ!!
♪♪～
《反撃するﾋﾏを与えるな！
Don't give him time to fight back.
息さえさせるな！
Don't let him breathe.
もう ﾁｬﾝｽは 二度とねえ！
There won't be another chance...
これで決めなきゃ 負ける！
If I don't finish him here, I'll lose.
終わりにするんだ!!》
It ends here!
うぉぉぉ～っ!!
ぐぉっ!!
This is...
これで… しめえだ～!!
The end!
ぐはっ…!!
♪♪～
くっ… ｷｻﾏ…！
B-Bastard...
ｷｻﾏ～!!
You...bastard!!
でやぁぁぁ～っ!!
♪♪～
(晴太)これか！
Is this it?!
晴太君！
早く！
Seita-kun!
Hurry!
♪♪～
[Unlock]
《ｵｲﾗだって…！》
I can also...
We must fight.
((日輪:戦わなきゃ…
檻の中で戦わなきゃ…➡
We must fight from inside the cage.
檻を蹴破らなきゃ…➡
If we don't smash through this cage, we'll never obtain true freedom.
本当の自由なんて
手に入りゃしない…｡
最後まで戦わせとくれ 晴太…))
Let me fight to the end, Seita.
戦うんだ～!!
Fight!!
(鳳仙)うぉぉぉ～っ!!
(月詠)うてぇぇ～っ!!
Fire!
♪♪～
はぁ… はぁ… はぁ…｡
(月詠たち)はぁ… はぁ… はぁ…｡
やった… ついに…➡
We finally...did it!
やった…！
鳳仙を… あの夜王を
ついに倒した!! 自由だ!!
We defeated Hosen... We finally defeated the King of the Night! We're free!
(百華)これで 吉原は…➡
Now Yoshiwara is... We are...free!
私たちは… 自由だ!!
…まだだ～!!
Not yet!
ぐっ… うっ…｡
ぎ… 銀時!!
G-Gintoki!
(笑い声)
ぬるい… ぬるいわ!!
Weak! Weak!!
ｷｻﾏらごとき
か細き光が いくら集まろうと➡
You can assemble as many faint rays of light as you want.
この夜王を干乾びさせることは
できはせぬ！
You still won't be able to dry out the King of the Night!
この深き夜を照らすことなど…➡
You cannot light up this dark night!
できはせぬわ!! てやぁぁ～っ!!
ﾊﾞ… ﾊﾞｶな…！
あれだけやっても まだ…！
I-Impossible!
After all that, he's still...?!
(口笛)
太陽などとは程遠い！
You're nothing like the sun.
吹けば一瞬で消える
ﾛｳｿｸの火のような脆弱な光｡
A frail light, like a candle that can be extinguished with a mere blow.
それが ｷｻﾏらだ!!
That's what you all are!
おとなしく死んだような目で
我が鎖につながれておれば➡
You should have stayed chained to me with eyes of despair.
生かしてやったものを｡
まさか 一度は
我らに消された残り火から➡
Though I never expected that you are flames to reignite...
飛び火をもらおうとは｡
from the remains of a fire once extinguished by us.
火種は消さねばなるまい｡
I must destroy the source of the fire, that...
その鈍く光る光を！
...dim light of yours!
待て！
Hold it.
もういい｡
もう ｵﾚだけで十分だ｡
That's enough.
My life is enough.
その火はとっときな｡
明日のたばこのためにな｡
Save that flare of yours,
for your cigarettes tomorrow.
(鳳仙)武士道とやらか｡
Is that your so-called "Bushido"?
殊勝なことだな｡
How honorable of you.
己一人の命を捧げて
女たちの免罪を乞おうというのか｡
Offering your own life in exchange for forgiving those women?
ﾌｯ… ﾑﾀﾞだ｡
ｷｻﾏが終われば 次は女たちだ｡
A futile effort.
Once I'm finished with you, the women are next.
消させやしねえさ… もう誰も｡
They won't be extinguished, none of them will.
たとえ か細いﾛｳｿｸの火でも…➡
Even if they're frail candles, if you gather enough, it can still illuminate the darkness.
集まりゃ 闇も照らせる｡
たとえ 火が消されても
一本でも火が残っていれば➡
Even if some are extinguished, as long as one remains lit, the rest can be re-lit.
また 火を灯せる｡
お前にゃ ｵﾚの火は消せねえよ｡
You can't blow out my flame.
何度吹き消そうとも ﾑﾀﾞな話だ｡
It's useless, no matter how hard you blow.
ｵﾚにゃ
とっておきの火種があるんだ｡
I have a special lighter with me.
絶対に消えねえ
火種がついてんだ｡
I've got a lighter that can never be extinguished.
ﾔﾂらがいるかぎり
ｵﾚは 何度消されても➡
As long as I have them,
I'll burst back into flames every time you blow them out.
何度でも燃え上がる！
うおおお～っ!!
ん？
な… なんだ!?
Wh...What?!
これは… この光は…!!
This...!
This light is...!!
お前なんぞに
ｵﾚたちの火は 消せやしねえ！
Someone like you can never blow out our flame!
♪♪～
何だ？ この揺れは！
What's with this shaking?!
見ろ！
Look!
Someone like you...
お前なんぞに…➡
ｵﾚたちの火は 消せやしねえ！
can never blow out our flame!
♪♪～
お前なんぞに…➡
Someone like you...
この光は 消せやしねえ！
can never extinguish this light!
こ… これは…！
Th-This is...
この光は まさかっ!!
This light is...!
It can't be...?!
♪♪～
ぐおおおっ…！
たっ… 太陽～っ!!
Th-The sun!!
ぐおおっ…！
ぐっ ぐおおお～っ!!
《血が… 肉が…
魂が渇いていく！》
My blood is...
My flesh is...
My soul is drying up!
(２人)いけえぇぇ～っ!!
Go!
(晴太/新八/神楽)銀さ～ん!!
Gin-san!!
うおおおっ!!
(新八/神楽)夜王の鎖を…➡
Burn off the chains...
焼き切れえぇぇ～っ!!
おおぉぉぉ～っ!!
of the King of the Night!!
(２人)うおおおお～っ!!
((ねぇねぇ おじちゃん｡
Hey, Mister.
Why are you using an umbrella when it's so sunny?
なんで こんなに晴れてるのに➡
傘なんて差してるの？
ねぇ なんで？
Why?
これ！
Hey!
How dare you speak to Lord Hosen like that?!
鳳仙様に何という口を利くんだ！
I am terribly sorry, Lord Hosen.
申し訳ありませぬ 鳳仙様｡
She's just a country girl who knows nothing.
何も知らぬ田舎娘なもので➡
どうか お許しを｡
Please forgive her.
Come on, let's go.
ほれ 行くぞ｡
Poor thing.
かわいそう｡
You can't even look at such a beautiful sky.
こんなきれいな空を➡
眺めることもできないなんて｡
Hey, Mister.
ねぇねぇ おじちゃん｡
Why do you live underground?
おじちゃんは どうして
こんな土の中に住んでるの？
Do you hate the sun that much?
そんなに お日様が嫌いなの？
Or does the sun hate you?
それとも おじちゃんが
お日様に嫌われてるの？
What are you doing, you idiot?!
何やってんだい ﾊﾞｶ！
I'm so sorry, Lord Hosen.
すみません 鳳仙様｡
ほら 行くよ！
Come on, let's go!
Mister, you shouldn't fight with the sun!
(日輪)おじちゃん ﾀﾞﾒだよ
お日様とｹﾝｶなんてしたら！
Stupid brat!
このｶﾞｷが！
I see you're working hard.
ずいぶんと精が出るな｡
L-Lord Hosen.
鳳仙様｡
お前は…｡
You're...
ﾌﾝｯ 今度は何をやらかした？
What did she do this time?
W-Well, she...
いえ あの その…｡
見せよ 後ろに隠しているそれを｡
Show me what you're hiding behind your back.
I'm terribly sorry!
申し訳ありません｡
She insisted on giving this to you.
どうしても鳳仙様に
これを渡すと聞かぬものですから｡
♪♪～
[For Mister]
Mister...
おじちゃん｡
Bear with that for now, okay?
今は それで我慢してね｡
でも いつかきっと➡
But I'm sure that one day,
私が おじちゃんとお日様を
仲直りさせてあげるからね｡
I'll help you and the sun make up.
Fawning upon the man who took you from your family to sell you off.
己を家族から引き裂き➡
売り物にした男に
媚びが売れるとは…｡
If you can do that with your customers, you have a future here.
それが客にできるようになれば➡
末は太夫も夢じゃなかろうて｡
It doesn't matter who you are.
(日輪)誰だって関係ないよ｡
Mister, the sun shines above every person.
おじちゃん お日様は
どんな人の上にも➡
同じに輝くんだよ｡
It gives light to everyone.
みんなに光を当ててくれるんだよ｡
おじちゃんの上にも きっと➡
It shines above you, too...
きっと冷たくなった
おじちゃんの心を温めてくれる｡
I'm sure it'll warm your chilled heart.
だから おじちゃん➡
So, Mister,
don't hate the sun.
お日様を嫌いにならないでね｡
My sworn enemy...
(鳳仙)我が天敵よ｡
After all these years, you still haven't changed.
久しぶりに会っても
何も変わらぬなぁ｡
はるか高みから
この夜王を見下ろしおって｡
You still look down on the King of the Night from high above.
Indeed...  So aggravating...
まったく なんと忌々しい｡
Yet...
だが➡
What a beautiful sight...
なんと美しい姿よ｡
How pitiful people are.
(神威)人とは哀れなものだね｡
己にないものほど欲しくなる｡
They always yearn for what they don't have.
届かぬものにほど手を伸ばす｡
They always reach out to what can't be reached.
What does the King of the Night lack? That would be light.
夜王にないもの それは光｡
旦那 あなたは太陽のせいで
渇いていたんじゃない｡
Boss, you didn't dry up because of the sun.
あなたは
太陽がないことに渇いていたんだ｡
You were thirsty for the sun.
誰よりも疎み 憎みながらも➡
As you shunned and hated it more than anyone else,
誰よりも うらやみ
焦がれていたんだ｡
you envied and yearned for it more than anyone else.
ｵﾚたちが決して
手に入れることのできない太陽に｡
To the sun we could never obtain...
冷たい戦場ではなく
温かい光の下で生きることに｡
Not to live on the cold battlefield,
but under a warm sun.
決して消えない その目の光に｡
To the undying light within their eyes.
ゆえに その光を奪った女たちを
己のいる夜へ➡
Hence, you dragged the women who had taken that light into your own night,
この常夜の国に引きずり込んだ｡
into this land of eternal night.
そして それでも
なお 消えぬ光を➡
And when that light still wouldn't fade, you could only hate,
憎み 愛したんだ｡
...and love.
(鳳仙)ｸｸｸ…｡
愛？ いったい そんな言葉
どこで覚えてきた？ 神威｡
Love?
Where did you learn such a word?
Kamui, you know more than anyone that I have no such emotion.
そんなもの ﾜｼが持ち得ぬのは➡
ｷｻﾏが いちばん
よく知っているはずだ｡
ﾜｼと同じ道を歩む
ｷｻﾏであれば 神威｡
If you're walking down the same path as me.
Kamui, you are just like me.
お前は ﾜｼと同じだ｡
A person who only knows how to fight.
戦う術しか知らぬ｡
欲しいものは
すべて戦って力ずくで奪う｡
You take everything you want by force.
気に食わぬものも すべて戦って
力ずくで ねじ伏せる｡
You hold down everything you dislike by force.
愛も憎しみも 戦うことでしか
表現する術を知らぬ｡
You can only express love and hate through fighting.
神威 お前も いずれ知ろう｡
Kamui, you will eventually learn.
年老い 己が来た道を
振り返ったとき…｡
When you're old and look back at the path you took,
我らの道には何もない｡
you'll find that our path is empty.
本当に欲しいものを前にしても
それを抱きしめる腕もない｡
Even when you find something you truly desire,
you lack the arms to hold it.
爪を つきたてることしかできぬ｡
You can only sink your claws into it.
引き寄せれば引き寄せるほど
爪は深く食い込む｡
The more you try to bring it closer,
the deeper your claws sink in.
手を伸ばせば伸ばすほど
遠く離れていく｡
The more you reach out for them,
the further away they go.
((日輪:おじちゃん
お日様は どんな人の上にも➡
Mister, the sun shines above every person.
同じに輝くんだよ｡
みんなに
光を当ててくれるんだよ))
It gives light to everyone.
なぜ お前さえもﾜｼを嫌う…｡
Why must you hate me, as well?
((日輪:おじちゃんの上にも
きっと…➡
It shines above you, too...
きっと冷たくなった
おじちゃんの心を温めてくれる))
I'm sure it'll warm your chilled heart...
なぜ お前さえﾜｼを拒む｡
Why must you reject me, as well?
((日輪:だから おじちゃん
お日様を嫌いにならないでね))
So, Mister,
don't hate the sun.
(鳳仙)なぜ こんなにも
焦がれているのに…｡
Why...  When I desire you so...
I am drying up...
ﾜｼは 渇いていく｡
見えぬ もう何も…｡
I can see nothing at all...
《いかなる光も届かぬ真の夜》
A true night, where no light can reach...
♪♪～
《死してなお➡
So, even in death, the King of the Night must walk into the night...
夜をゆくが夜王の運命か》
♪♪～
《これは…➡
This is...
この光は…》
This light is...
♪♪～
ひ… 日輪…｡
Hi-Hinowa...
♪♪～
[Preview]
I was finally able to show you...
I've wanted to show you this for the longest time...
Show you this sky...
[The next episode: "The Taste of Drinking Under Broad Daylight Is Something Special."]
[Finally, next week...]
[The Yoshiwara Shangri-La Arc draws to a close.]
[See you next time.]